Guide to the Northern Pacific Railway Company Records 1870-1968
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
- Advertising and Publicity Department, 1895-1950; Subgroup 3; 2.5 linear feet, 24 moving image items, and 2 oversize boxes
  - Moving Images, circa 1920s-1940; Series LX; 20 16mm film reels and 4 VHS tapes
    - Original Positive: Oto Ranch, Corwin Springs Montana, undated; 128(LX):11; Dude Ranch and Rodeo Scene; 16 mm; Black and White, 366 ft, No Sound; Digital Copy Available
    - OTO Ranch: Corwin springs Montana, ca. 1940s; 128(LX):12; Dude Ranch Scenes; 16 mm; Black and White, 271 ft, No Sound VHS Copy Available
    - Ranch Holiday #121, ca. 1940s; 128(LX):13; OTO Ranch, Corwin Springs, Montana; Filmed at the Sixty-three and OTO ranches, Montana; Dude ranch, rodeo, Native American Reservation Trip Scenes; 16 mm; Black and White, 366 ft, No Sound; Digital Copy Available
    - Dude Ranchers Positive Film, ca. 1940s; 128(LX):13/2; 16 mm; Black and White, 350 ft, No Sound VHS Copy Available
    - Its True Dudes on the Range, Sixty-Three Ranch, Undated; 128(LX):14; Livingston, Montana; Note: Film stock 1977- duplication of original film, date of original footage unknown VHS Copy Available; 16 mm; Black and White, 425 ft, No Sound
    - Dude Ranchers Reduction Original, ca. 1940s; 128(LX):15; 16 mm; Black and White, 267 ft, No Sound
    - Wildlife, ca. 1940s; 128(LX):16; 2 parts; 16 mm; Black and White, 297 ft, No Sound
    - Alaska Ahoy! Positive Film, ca. 1960s; 128(LX):17; Boat trip from Seattle to Alaska, Salmon Fishing, Native American Totem Poles, Seals, Gold Dredging in Fairbanks, Alaska; 16 mm; Black and White, 400 ft, No Sound
    - A playground in Paradise / Mt. Baker Park Film Positive, ca. 1950s-1960s; 128(LX):18; Mt. Baker, Washington. Mountaineering; 16 mm; Black and White, 350 ft, No Sound
    - A Playground in Paradise, ca. 1950s-1960s; 128(LX):18/2; Mt. Baker, Washington. Mountaineering; 16 mm; Black and White, 350 ft, No Sound
    - Meet the Mountain Film Positive, ca. 1950s; 128(LX):19; Mt. Rainier, Washington. Mountaineering; 16 mm; Black and White, 400 ft, No Sound
    - Rainier National Park Film Positive, ca. 1940s; 128(LX):20; Driving Tour of Washington. Yakima, Washington, fruit orchards, mountaineering.; 16 mm; Black and White Emulsion- Red and Blue tinted film stock, 400 ft, No Sound
    - Video transfer of reels 128(LX):8 and 128(LX):11 through 128(LX):15, undated; 128(LX):21
  - Photographs, 1895-1950; Series LXI; 2.5 linear feet and 2 oversize boxes
    This series includes photographs generated by the promotions department of the railway. These photographs appear to have been intended for promotional literature, particularly to highlight the agricultural potential of the high plains and river valleys along Northern Pacific Railway routes. The majority of these photographs were captured after the first major homesteading wave in the region (1890s through 1918) and during the disastorous cycles of high plains droughts that resulted in farm foreclosures and homesteader emmigration (1919 through 1933). These photographs depicting agricultural abundance and opportunity present images in marked contrast to the tenor of agricultural studies and regional news reports during the period.
    In addition, the photographs in this series present images of the towns and landscapes along the railway routes during the early stages of industrial production in the region--when the impact of railroad access is evidenced by transformations in agricultural and timber harvesting methods as well as the capacity of transporting high volume goods to distant markets. Though this series contains photographs spanning the Northern Pacific line, the images predominantly depict the farms and rail hub towns of Montana and Idaho during the 1920s and 1930s. Also included are some documentary images of Northern Pacific promotional exhibits which help to reveal additional context for how the department used the other photographs in this series.
    - Agriculture: Barns, 1922 - 1927 and undated (Box-folder 398/1)
    - Agriculture: Bees, 1928 and undated (Box-folder 398/2)
    - Agriculture: Bitterroot Valley, Montana - Homes, and People, undated (Box-folder 398/3)
    - Agricultrue: Bitterroot Valley, Montana - Rural Scences, 1927 and undated (Box-folder 398/4)
    - Agriculture: Butchering Technique, 1931 (Box-folder 398/5)
    - Agriculture: Cattle, Montana, 1927 - 1950 and undated (Box-folder 398/6)
    - Agriculture: Cattle, Other locations, 1922 - 1928 and undated (Box-folder 398/7)
    - Agriculture: Cattle, Other Locations, 1927 - 1950 and undated (Box-folder 398/8)
    - Agriculture: Cattle, Dairy, 1934 and undated (Box-folder 398/9)
    - Agriculture: Corn, undated (Box-folder 398/10)
    - Agriculture: Exhibits and Displays, undated (Box-folder 398/11)
    - Agriculture: Exhibits and Displays, undated (Box-folder 398/12)
    - Agriculture: Expositions and Displays, 1913 - 1931 and undated (Box-folder 399/1)
    - Agriculture: Expositions and Displays, 1912 - 1932 and undated (Box-folder 399/2)
    - Agriculture: Expositions and Displays, 1926 - 1950 and undated (Box-folder 399/3)
    - Agriculture: Farm Machinery, 1928 - 1939 and undated (Box-folder 399/4)
    - Agriculture: Fruit and Berries, 1909 - 1931 and undated (Box-folder 399/5)
    - Agriculture: Flathead Valley, Montana, 1915 - 1928 and undated (Box-folder 399/6)
    - Agriculture: 4 H Club Conference, Bozeman, Montana, 1930 - 1933 and undated (Box-folder 399/7)
    - Agriculture: Field Production and Distribution, 1909 - 1935 and undated (Box-folder 399/8)
    - Agriculture: Fox Farm, Atrium, Minnesota, 1927-08 (Box-folder 399/9)
    - Agriculture: Goats, 1934 and undated (Box-folder 399/10)
    - Agriculture: Grain, 1918 - 1931 and undated (Box-folder 400/1)
    - Agriculture: Grasshopper eradication, 1938 and undated (Box-folder 400/2)
    - Agriculture: Haying, 1921 - 1931 and undated (Box-folder 400/3)
    - Agriculture: Hops, 1937 and undated (Box-folder 400/4)
    - Agriculture: Horses, 1938 and undated (Box-folder 400/5)
    - Agriculture: Irrigation, Bitterroot Valley, Montana, undated (Box-folder 400/6)
    - Agriculture: Irrigation, General, 1923 - 1936 and undated (Box-folder 400/7)
    - Agriculture: Land Clearing, 1927 - 1938 and undated (Box-folder 400/8)
    - Agriculture: Land Promotion, 1929 - 1931 and undated (Box-folder 400/9)
    - Agriculture: Mt. Haggin Land and Livestock Company, Montana, 1928 - 1931 (Box-folder 400/10)
    - Agriculture: Potatoes, 1948 and undated (Box-folder 400/11)
    - Agriculture: Poultry, 1924 - 1934 and undated (Box-folder 400/12)
    - Agriculture: Publication, undated (Box-folder 400/13)
    - Agriculture: Rabbits, undated (Box-folder 400/14)
    - Agriculture: Sheep, 1927 - 1939 and undated (Box-folder 401/1)
    - Agriculture: Sugar Beet, 1927 - 1928 and undated (Box-folder 401/2)
    - Agriculture: Swine, 1927 - 1947 and undated (Box-folder 401/3)
    - Arlee, Montana, 1929 (Box-folder 401/4)
    - Bayers, A.C., undated (Box-folder 401/5)
    - Beaver Valley, Montana, undated (Box-folder 401/6)
    - Big Timber, Montana, circa 1922 (Box-folder 401/7)
    - Billings, Montana, 1911 - 1931 and undated (Box-folder 401/8)
    - Bitterroot Dam Reservoir, undated (Box-folder 401/9)
    - Bitterroot River, undated (Box-folder 401/10)
    - Bozeman, Montana, 1918 - 1923 and undated (Box-folder 401/11)
    - Bozeman, Montana, University campus, undated (Box-folder 401/12)
    - Buffalo, Montana, undated (Box-folder 401/13)
    - Buffalo Rapids, Montana, 1941 (Box-folder 401/14)
    - Burbank Pumphouse, undated (Box-folder 401/15)
    - Butte, Montana, undated (Box-folder 401/16)
    - Butte, Montana, Orphan Girl Mine, undated (Box-folder 401/17)
    - Charlo, Montana, 1928 - 1929 and undated (Box-folder 401/18)
    - Couer d'Alene, Idaho, undated (Box-folder 401/19)
    - Corvallis, Montana, undated (Box-folder 401/20)
    - Cottonwood, Idaho, 1923 (Box-folder 401/21)
    - Deer Lodge, Montana, undated (Box-folder 401/22)
    - Fairview, Montana, undated (Box-folder 401/23)
    - Fallon County Rural School, 1925 (Box-folder 401/24)
    - Fishing Industry, Oregon, 1931 (Box-folder 401/25)
    - Forsyth, Montana, 1928 and undated (Box-folder 401/26)
    - Fromberg, Montana, undated (Box-folder 401/27)
    - Glendive, Montana, undated (Box-folder 401/28)
    - Grangeville, Idaho, 1922 (Box-folder 401/29)
    - Hamilton, Montana, Canning Factory, undated (Box-folder 401/30)
    - Hamilton, Montana, Chamber of Commerce Building, undated (Box-folder 401/31)
    - Hamilton, Montana, undated (Box-folder 401/32)
    - Helena, Montana, 1930 and undated (Box-folder 401/33)
    - Hellgate Canyon, Montana, undated (Box-folder 401/34)
    - Hysham, Montana, 1932 and undated (Box-folder 401/35)
    - Idaho, 1923 and undated (Box-folder 401/36)
    - International Falls, Minnesota, Riverdale Farm, 1927 (Box-folder 401/37)
    - Kerr Dam, Montana, undated (Box-folder 401/38)
    - Lewiston, Idaho, undated (Box-folder 401/39)
    - Livingston, Montana, undated (Box-folder 401/40)
    - Lower Yellowstone Dam Project, 1910 (Box-folder 401/41)
    - Lumbering, Cedar Shake Production, undated (Box-folder 402/1)
    - Lumbering, 1924 - 1927 and undated (Box-folder 402/2)
    - Lumbering, sawmills, 1923, 1928, and undated (Box-folder 402/3)
    - Lumbering, water log drive, 1923 (Box-folder 402/4)
    - Lumbering, drag saw, 1924 (Box-folder 402/5)
    - Lumbering, railroads, 1913 and undated (Box-folder 402/6)
    - Lumbering, unusually large trees and logs, 1923 - 1928 and undated (Box-folder 402/7)
    - Manhattan, Montana, undated (Box-folder 402/8)
    - Meyers, Montana, Yellowstone Irrigation District, 1929 (Box-folder 402/9)
    - Miles City, Montana, undated (Box-folder 402/10)
    - Miles City, Montana, Hagen Ranch, undated (Box-folder 402/11)
    - Mining, coal, undated (Box-folder 402/12)
    - Minnesota, 1927, 1929 and undated (Box-folder 402/13)
    - Mission Mountains, Montana, 1928 and undated (Box-folder 402/14)
    - Missoula, Montana, 1923 (Box-folder 402/15)
    - Missoula, Montana, University campus, undated (Box-folder 402/16)
    - Montana Press Association, undated (Box-folder 402/17)
    - Moscow, Idaho, University campus, 1925 (Box-folder 402/18)
    - North Dakota, 1923 - 1928, 1947 and undated (Box-folder 402/19)
    - Noxon, Montana, undated (Box-folder 402/20)
    - Lake Pend Oreille, Idaho, undated (Box-folder 402/21)
    - Priest Rapids, Washington, undated (Box-folder 402/22)
    - Railroad Promotions, 1926 - 1927 and undated (Box-folder 402/23)
    - Recreation, boating, undated (Box-folder 402/24)
    - Red River District, Montana, undated (Box-folder 402/25)
    - Rimroad, Montana, 1929 (Box-folder 402/26)
    - St. Ignatius, Montana, 1895, 1925 - 1929 and undated (Box-folder 402/27)
    - St. Maries, Idaho, circa 1923 (Box-folder 402/28)
    - Salmon Lake, Montana, undated (Box-folder 402/29)
    - Sandpoint, Idaho, circa 1923 (Box-folder 402/30)
    - Seeley Lake, Montana, undated (Box-folder 402/31)
    - Shields Valley, Montana, undated (Box-folder 402/32)
    - Sidney, Montana, 1927 - 1929 and undated (Box-folder 402/33)
    - Swan River Valley, Montana, undated (Box-folder 402/34)
    - Thompson Falls, Montana, undated (Box-folder 402/35)
    - Transportation, early automobiles and trucks, no location, undated (Box-folder 402/36)
    - Transportation, farm wagons in Montana, undated (Box-folder 402/37)
    - Transportation, railroad locomotives, 1923 - 1936 (Box-folder 402/38)
    - Transportation, Northern Pacific Butte Line, undated (Box-folder 402/39)
    - Transportation, train wrecks, undated (Box-folder 402/40)
    - Transportation, sleighs, undated (Box-folder 402/41)
    - Transportation, steamboat, Portland, Oregon, undated (Box-folder 402/42)
    - Trout Creek, Montana, undated (Box-folder 402/43)
    - Twin Bridges, Montana, 1922, 1923 and undated (Box-folder 402/44)
    - Twin Bridges, Montana, Orphans Home, 1922 (Box-folder 402/45)
    - Washington state, 1923 - 1933 and undated (Box-folder 402/46)
    - Whitebird, Idaho, 1923 (Box-folder 402/47)
    - Northern Pacific Railway Exhibit, mounted photographs, no location, undated (Box-folder OS2)
    - Northern Pacific Railway Exhibit and General Promotional Photographs, various locations, undated (Box-folder OS3)